Rudolf Kolisch Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Rudolf Kolisch Collection 1921-1943
ML31.K63
Kolisch, Rudolf, 1896-1978
31 items 1 container 1 linear foot
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Rudolf Kolisch was a Viennese-American violinist and string quartet player. The collection contains thirty-one items, principally holograph manuscript correspondence, that provide insight into the professional relationship between Kolisch and composers Arnold Schoenberg, Alban Berg, and Anton Webern. Included among these are two Berg manuscripts that present analysis and musical examples from his Lyric suite and String quartet, op. 3.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Beethoven, Ludwig van, 1770-1827--Criticism and interpretation.; Berg, Alban, 1885-1935--Correspondence.; Berg, Alban, 1885-1935--Criticism and interpretation.; Berg, Alban, 1885-1935--Performances.; Berg, Alban, 1885-1935. Lyrische Suite.; Berg, Alban, 1885-1935. Quartet, strings, op. 3.; Kolisch, Rudolf, 1896-1978--Correspondence.; Kolisch, Rudolf, 1896-1978.; Kolisch, Rudolf, 1896-1978.; Schoenberg, Arnold, 1874-1951--Correspondence.; Schoenberg, Arnold, 1874-1951--Criticism and interpretation.; Schoenberg, Arnold, 1874-1951--Performances.; Webern, Anton, 1883-1945--Correspondence.; Webern, Anton, 1883-1945--Criticism and interpretation.; Webern, Anton, 1883-1945--Performances.
Form/Genre
Correspondence.
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift, Lorna Kolisch, 1983.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Access and Restrictions
The Rudolf Kolisch Collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Performing Arts Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
Rudolf Kolisch (1896-1978) was a prominent Viennese-American violinist and string quartet player who played his instrument left-handed as a result of a childhood injury. His Kolisch Quartet gave seminal performances and premieres of chamber music that included compositions by Arnold Schoenberg, Alban Berg, and Anton Webern. In 1935, Kolisch immigrated to the United States, where he developed a parallel career as a professor of music at the University of Wisconsin, the New England Conservatory of Music, and other institutions.
Date Event
1896 July 20 Born in Klamm, Austria
1913 Graduates from Vienna Music Academy and Vienna University
1919 Studies composition with Arnold Schoenberg
1919-1921 Plays a leading role in Schoenberg's "Verein für Musikalische Privataufführungen" (Society for Private Musical Performances)
1921 Forms the Wiener Streichquartett (Rudolf Kolisch, Fritz Rothschild, Marcel Dick, Joachim Stutschewsky)
1924 Arnold Schoenberg marries Kolisch's sister, Gertrud
1927 Forms the Kolisch Quartett (Rudolf Kolisch, Felix Khuner, Eugene Lehner, Benar Heifetz)
1935 Kolisch Quartett immigrates to the United States and makes its American debut performance at the Library of Congress
1939 Kolisch Quartett disbands
1939 Begins teaching at the New School for Social Research, New York
1943 Publishes his best known article, Tempo and character in Beethoven's music
1944 Becomes first violinist of Pro Arte Quartet
1944 Begins teaching at the University of Wisconsin
1953-1958 Teaches at the Akademie für Tonkunst and Ferienkurse für neue Musik in Darnstadt, Germany
1967 Begins teaching at the New England Conservatory of Music, Boston
1974-1977 Teaches chamber music performance at the annual Schoenberg Seminars in Mödling, Austria
1978 Aug. 1 Dies in Watertown, Massachusetts
Scope and Content Note
The Rudolf Kolisch Collection contains thirty-one items, principally manuscript correspondence, that provide insight into the professional relationship between Kolisch and composers Arnold Schoenberg, Alban Berg, and Anton Webern, from 1921-1943. The Musical Analysis and Examples series includes materials related to Berg's Lyric suite and String quartet, op. 3. The Correspondence series consists of postcards and letters, chiefly from Webern to Kolisch, that discuss compositional progress and upcoming performances. Among the works mentioned are Webern's String trio, op. 20, String quartet, op. 28, Six bagatelles, op. 9, Fünf Sätze, op. 5, Symphony, op. 21, and Variations for piano, op. 27, as well as various compositions by Schoenberg, Berg, and Beethoven.
Organization of the Rudolf Kolisch Collection
The Rudolf Kolisch Collection is organized in 3 series:
Musical Analysis and Examples
Correspondence
Miscellaneous
http://lccn.loc.gov/2010561022
Container List
- Musical Analysis and Examples (Box 1)
  - Berg, Alban (Box 1)
    - Analysis of Lyric suite, Holograph manuscript in ink, with additions in pencil; [9] p.; Principally tone rows and scales from movements nos. 1-6 with analytical commentary (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Fragebogen, Holograph manuscript with music in ink and text in pencil; [2] p.; 11 measures for String quartet, op. 3, (including an "ossia" line for violoncello) and 6 additional measures for one unspecified instrument; Both pages contain questions and comments concerning performance practice and playability (Box-folder 1/2)
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Arnold Schoenberg to RK, 1943 Dec. 2, Typescript letter with notes in pencil; [2] p.; Contents: expresses thanks for a gift; mentions work on "Counterpoint"; discusses RK's essay on tempo markings in Beethoven; asks if RK considered performing his "Ode"; asks for the source of a Beethoven quote (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Anton Webern to RK, 1921 July 25, Holograph manuscript postcard in black ink; Contents: expresses thanks for a gift; mentions Schoenberg and his [AW's] orchestration of Schoenberg's "Glückliche Hand" for chamber orchestra (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Anton Webern to RK, 1927 Aug. 13, Holograph manuscript postcard in black ink; Contents: mentions sending his music for printing to Universal Edition; references "Trio" premiere on Oct. 1 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Anton Webern to RK, 1927 Aug. 23, Holograph manuscript postcard in black ink; Contents: references "Trio" premiere on Oct. 1 and Universal Edition (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Anton Webern to RK, 1927 Sept. 7, Holograph manuscript postcard in black ink; Contents: references "Trio" performance on Oct. 1; responds to RK's concern of not being able to play; asks RK to return the original score if possible (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Anton Webern to RK, 1927 Sept. 21, Holograph manuscript postcard in black ink; Contents: mentions "Bagatellen" and performance suggestions for the work; references "Trio" performance in Cologne (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Anton Webern to RK, 1928 July 14, Holograph manuscript postcard in black ink; Contents: mentions "Trio" performance in Siena; RK's pleusiry; Fr. Herlinger; performance of an evening song recital in London (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Anton Webern to RK, 1928 July 19, Holograph manuscript postcard blue-purple pencil; Contents: mentions possible meeting with RK in Aussee (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Anton Webern to RK, 1928 Sept. 22, Holograph manuscript postcard in black ink; Contents: mentions performance of "Trio" in Siena and possible meeting in Aussee (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Anton Webern to RK, 1929 Apr. 1, Holograph manuscript postcard in black ink; Contents: mentions rescheduled choir rehearsal and possible meeting (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Anton Webern to RK, 1921 Aug. 8, Holograph manuscript letter in black ink; [2] p.; Contents: encourages RK to stay with the theater; mentions Schoenberg (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Anton Webern to RK, 1924 Mar. 4, Holograph manuscript letter in black ink; [2] p.; Contents: mentions performance opportunity mediated by Loos, suggesting the first "Quartet" and "Violinstücke" (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Anton Webern to RK, 1927 June 13, Holograph manuscript letter in black ink; [1] p.; Contents: mentions accompanying letter of recommendation for Fr. Rosanska to Koussevitzki [missing]; discusses possible rehearsal date of Schoenberg's "Suite" (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Anton Webern to RK, 1927 Oct. 9, Holograph manuscript letter in black ink; [2] p.; Contents: mentions possible premiere of "Trio" at the end of Nov.; references "Bagatellen" and Schoenberg (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Anton Webern to RK, 1928 Jan. 20, Holograph manuscript letter in black ink; [2] p.; Contents: expresses thanks to RK, Mr. Khuner, and Heifetz for a great first performance of "Trio" (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Anton Webern to RK, 1928 Mar. 11, Holograph manuscript letter in black ink; [2] p.; Contents: mentions "Trio" and issues with A.D.M.V. and city of Schwerin concerning an upcoming performance (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Anton Webern to RK, 1928 Mar. 17, Holograph manuscript letter in black ink; [1] p.; Contents: summarizes aforementioned issue with Schwerin/A.D.M.V.; references accompanying response letter [missing] (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Anton Webern to RK, 1929 July 1, Holograph manuscript letter in black ink; [1] p.; Contents: mentions his involvement with the radio station Ravag and invites RK to perform a cycle of contemporary chamber music, specifically quartets by Schoenberg (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Anton Webern to RK, 1931 Mar. 21, Holograph manuscript letter in black ink; [2] p.; Contents: mentions "5 Sätze" and "Quartet"; references to Schoenberg, Beethoven, Ast, Ms. Herlinger, Frl. Michalski, and Frl. Rozanska (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Anton Webern to RK, 1934 Oct. 4, Holograph manuscript letter in black ink; [2] p.; Contents: mentions gala event for Schoenberg ("Schoenberg-Feier") in the "Verein für neue Musik"; references to Jalowetz, Steuermann, and Stein; asks if RK can play "Quartet I and III" for the occasion (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Anton Webern to RK, 1936 Nov. 7, Holograph manuscript letter in black ink; [3] p.; Contents: mentions success of RK's quartet in the U.S.; talks about "Verein für neue Musik" and Schoenberg gala event that will feature his latest "Quartet" and "Waldtaube", with Klemperer conducting "Streicher-Suite"; references to Berg's violin concerto, his own symphony; completion of a variation composition for piano and work on a string quartet; mentions Peter and Steuermann (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Anton Webern to RK, 1937 Mar. 31, Holograph manuscript letter in black ink; [2] p.; Contents: references messages from London and discusses public performance of his "Quartet IV" by RK in Vienna; suggests Berg's "Quartet" for performance and mentions possibility of Steuermann playing his "Variationen"; asks for possible dates for performances (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Anton Webern to RK, 1937 May 31, Holograph manuscript letter in black-blue ink; [2] p.; Contents: mentions possible meeting the following Monday in Vienna and RK's quartet performance of his "5 Stücke" (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Anton Webern to RK, 1937 Dec. 22, Holograph manuscript letter in black ink; [2] p.; Contents: mentions "Wind quintet" and "Quartet"; references to RK's performance of the "5 Sätze" in New York, E.S. Coolidge, and Schoenberg (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Anton Webern to RK, 1938 Apr. 19, Holograph manuscript letter in black ink; [4] p.; Contents: description and analysis of his String quartet, op. 28 in folder entitled: "Analyse Streichquartett" (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Anton Webern to RK, 1938 Dec. 1, Holograph manuscript letter in black ink; [2] p.; Contents: mentions Schoenberg, E. S. Coolidge, Boosey and Hawkes, Steuermann, daughter Christl and grand-daughter; discussion of first performance of "Quartet" (Sept. 22) and a later performance in NY (Nov. 1); talks about possibly recording the "Quartet" (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Anton Webern to RK, 1938 Aug. 17, Holograph manuscript letter in black ink; [2] p.; Contents: mentions his "Quartet", work on a symphony, Greissle, Steuermann, and financial matters (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Anton Webern to RK, 1939 Mar. 30, Holograph manuscript letter in black ink; [1] p.; Contents: mentions Coolidge Medal, Schoenberg, an upcoming performance of his [AW's] "Quartet" in Warsaw, and work on a symphony with text by Hildegard Jone [op. 29] (Box-folder 1/10)
- Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - [Unidentified drawing of a stage?], Crayon; [2] boards (Box-folder 1/11)